And here is my code.
これが そのコードです
In the process measurement function,
プロセス計測関数で
I first update the state transition matrix, F,
まず 状態遷移行列 F それから
and the process covariance matrix,
プロセス共分散行列 Q を 新しい
Q, based on new elapsed time.
直近の経過時間に基づいて更新します
And finally, I call the Kalman filter predict and update.
最後に カルマンフィルターpredictを 呼び出して 更新します
Let me show you, actually,
ビジュアライゼーションが どうなるか
how the visualization of our results would look.
実際に お見せしましょう
Say, that our pedestrian is moving in a kind of figure eight.
ここでは 歩行者が 8の字を描いて 歩いています
And as you see here,
ご覧の とおり
the orange dots are our laser measurements,
オレンジの点は レーザー測定値 つまり
which is basically the observed px and py position.
観測されたpxと pyの 位置です
The green line is the real path of the pedestrian,
緑の線が 歩行者の実際の経路
or in other words, the ground truth.
つまり グランドトルースです
And the blue line is the estimated position resulted from our Kalman filter solution.
そして 青い線が カルマンフィルターの解による 推定位置です
The estimated trajectory actually might look different
推定したトラジェクトリーは 計測ノイズや プロセスノイズの
depending on how we choose the measurement or process noises.
選択方法によって 異なる可能性があります
For example, here, I increase the measurement noise so the measurement covariance matrix,
たとえば ここで 計測ノイズを 増加させ 計測共分散行列Rの
R, has two on the diagonal line.
対角成分が 2に なるようにします
If I zoom in,
拡大して
then we can have a look closer at
細かく 見てみると
the estimated results compared to the measurements and the ground truth.
推定結果を 測定値や グラウンドトルースと 比べることができます
It works quite well when the pedestrian is moving along the straight line.
歩行者が 直線的に 動いているところでは かなりよく推定されています
However, our linear motion model is not perfect,
しかし 線形モーションモデルは 完璧ではなく
especially for the scenarios when the pedestrian is
特に 歩行者が このように
moving along a circular path, as you see here.
カーブを描いて 動くと 正確でなくなります
We always predict that
私たちは 歩行者が
the pedestrian position would be somewhere along the straight line,
常に 直線に沿って 動くと予測してしまうのですが
although their real position follows the green trajectory.
実際には 緑のトラジェクトリーに 沿っているわけです
So, our estimation would actually underestimate the truth state.
そのため 推定が 実際の状態を 過小評価してしまいます
So, how can we solve this?
これは どうすれば 解決できるでしょうか
Well, instead of using the linear motion model,
線形モーションモデルを 使うのではなく
we can predict the state by using
円周運動などの 複雑なモーションモデルを
a more complex motion model such as the circular motion.
使って 推定する方法が あります
But you will learn about that in the next lesson.
それについては 次のレッスンで 学習します
Great. Now that we can update with laser data,
それでは、レーザーデータで更新できるようになったので、
let us see what we can do with radar data.
レーザーデータの使い方を見てみましょう
That is the power of the Kalman filter.
それこそが カルマンフィルターの実力です
It can use multiple data sources originating from
異なるセンサーから 得た データソースを使って
different sensors to estimate a more accurate object state.
物体の状態を より正確に 推定できます